A Guide to the Daniel J. Kevles papers FA497
Rockefeller Archive Center
- David Baltimore Case Research Files, 1955-2000; 2; 12.16 Cubic Feet 32 document boxes: 32 letter boxes
  - Case research and book preparation, 1955-2000; 2; 7.885 Cubic Feet 20.75 document boxes: 20.75 letter boxes
    - David Goodstein and Jim Woodward - California Institute of Technology book on research ethics, 1994-1999 (Box 13, Folder 144)
    - David Goodstein and Jim Woodward - Scientific misconduct and fraud, 1983-1997 (Box 13, Folder 145)
    - Articles - Scientific fraud, historical cases, 1990-1994 (Box 14, Folder 146)
    - Immunology - Articles and interview notes, 1968-1992 (Box 14, Folder 147)
    - Edward Golub - Immunology, 1992-1993 (Box 14, Folder 148)
    - Account of the experiment - Thereza Imanishi-Kari and David Baltimore comments, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 149)
    - Background on Cell paper - Articles, 1971-1996 (Box 14, Folder 150)
    - Extensions - Cell paper, 1987-1996 (Box 14, Folder 151-152)
    - Joan Press and David Parker, 1990-1997 (Box 14, Folder 153)
    - David Feynman "The Uncreative Scientist" February 7, 1967 talk, 1997 (Box 15, Folder 154)
    - Bernard Davis, 1986-1997 (Box 15, Folder 155)
    - Bernard David manuscript, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 156)
    - Philip Sharp letter, 1989-1990 (Box 15, Folder 157)
    - Philip Hilts - Reporting on Thereza Imanishi-Kari case, 1991-1996 (Box 15, Folder 158)
    - June 1991 tape notes, 1997 (Box 15, Folder 159)
    - Normand F. Smith, 1995-1996 (Box 15, Folder 160)
    - Rockefeller University, 1989-1997 (Box 15, Folder 161)
    - Mark Ptashne, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 162)
    - John Deutch, 1986-1997 (Box 15, Folder 163)
    - David Baltimore - Cell paper investigation, 1967-1997 (Box 15, Folder 164-165)
    - David Baltimore - Chronology of events, 1970-1992 (Box 15, Folder 166)
    - Whitehead Institute - History and controversy, 1981-1997 (Box 16, Folder 167)
    - David Baltimore - Oral history interviews by Sondra Schlesinger, 1994-1997 (Box 16, Folder 168)
    - David Baltimore - Maxine Singer, 1988-1997 (Box 16, Folder 169)
    - Normand F. Smith correspondence, 1989-1997 (Box 16, Folder 170)
    - David Baltimore - Articles and biographical sketch, 1996-1997 (Box 16, Folder 171)
    - Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI) draft report on Cell paper investigation, 1991-1997 (Box 16, Folder 172)
    - Robert Gallo AIDS discovery case, 1987-1997 (Box 16, Folder 173-174)
    - Robert Gallo AIDS discovery case - Peter Neushul report, 1996 July 31 (Box 16, Folder 175)
    - Office of Research Integrity (ORI) final report - Response, 1994 (Box 16, Folder 176)
    - Office of Research Integrity (ORI) final report, 1994 (Box 16, Folder 177)
    - Herman Eisen - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1979-1997 (Box 17, Folder 178)
    - Thereza Imanishi-Kari responses to Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI), 1990-1997 (Box 17, Folder 179-180)
    - Thereza Imanishi-Kari Office of Research Integrity (ORI) appeal - Notes, 1995-1997 (Box 17, Folder 181)
    - Thereza Imanishi-Kari Office of Research Integrity (ORI) appeal - Analysis, 1978-1997 (Box 17, Folder 182)
    - Thereza Imanishi-Kari Office of Research Integrity (ORI) appeal, 1993-1997 (Box 17, Folder 183)
    - Thereza Imanishi-Kari Office of Research Integrity (ORI) appeal - Department Appeals Board (DAB), 1997 (Box 17, Folder 184)
    - United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) Department Appeals Board (DAB) decisions, 1996 (Box 18, Folder 185)
    - Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI) investigation report on Cell paper, 1990-1997 (Box 18, Folder 186)
    - Books and articles on Thereza Imanishi-Kari case, 1988-1994 (Box 18, Folder 187)
    - Mikulas Popovic suit against Suzanne Hadley and United States - Decision, 1998 (Box 18, Folder 188)
    - Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI) draft report on Robert Gallo HIV research, 1991-1997 (Box 18, Folder 189-190)
    - 1993 Office of Research Integrity (ORI)/American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) Conference on Plagiarism and Theft of Ideas report, 1993-1996 (Box 18, Folder 191)
    - Professional Ethics Report and Office of Research Integrity (ORI) newsletter copies, 1991-2000 (Box 18, Folder 192)
    - Scientific fraud and misconduct procedures - News clippings and articles from 1992 and after, 1990-1996 (Box 19, Folder 193)
    - W.W. Norton and Company publisher - Lawyer, 1997 (Box 19, Folder 194)
    - The Times Higher Education Supplement (THES) piece about book, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 195)
    - Book corrections for second printing, 1998-1999 (Box 19, Folder 196)
    - Book index corrections, circa 1997-1998 (Box 19, Folder 197)
    - David Baltimore case interviews summaries, 1993-1996 (Box 19, Folder 198)
    - David Baltimore case interviews summaries, 1997 (Box 19, Folder 199)
    - American Society for Microbiology (ASM) Public Communications Award nomination, 1996-1997 (Box 19, Folder 200)
    - "To dos" for manuscript, 1996 (Box 19, Folder 201)
    - Horace Judson, 1996 (Box 19, Folder 202)
    - Daniel Kevles article in Engineering and Science about David Baltimore case, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 203)
    - Daniel Kevles University of Southern California lecture on David Baltimore case, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 204)
    - Discover, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 205)
    - Daniel Kevles visit to University of California Berkeley, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 206)
    - Daniel Kevles talk at Stanford University, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 207)
    - Daniel Kevles talks at Stanford University and Commonwealth Club of California, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 208)
    - La Recherche, 1998 (Box 19, Folder 209)
    - Daniel Kevles lecture at University of Illinois, Chicago Circle, 1997 (Box 19, Folder 210)
    - David Baltimore case - Remarks and news clips, 1991-1998 (Box 19, Folder 211)
    - Daniel Kevles Massachusetts Institute of Technology lecture, 1996 (Box 19, Folder 212)
    - David Baltimore case press coverage - Newspaper indexes, 1986-1993 (Box 19, Folder 213)
    - David Baltimore case press coverage - 1988 articles and news clippings (Box 20, Folder 214)
    - David Baltimore case press coverage - 1990 articles and news clippings, 1990-1996 (Box 20, Folder 215)
    - David Baltimore case press coverage - 1989 articles and news clippings (Box 20, Folder 216)
    - David Baltimore case press coverage - January-June 1991 articles and news clippings, 1991-1996 (Box 20, Folder 217)
    - David Baltimore case press coverage - July-December 1991 articles and news clippings, 1991-1995 (Box 20, Folder 218)
    - Nature 1991 letter war - Responses after Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI) draft report (Box 20, Folder 219)
    - John D. Dingell Shattuck Lecture and responses, 1993 (Box 21, Folder 220)
    - David Baltimore case press coverage - 1992 articles and news clippings, 1992-1997 (Box 21, Folder 221)
    - David Baltimore case press coverage - 1996-1997 articles, circa 1996-1997 (Box 21, Folder 222)
    - Miscellaneous materials related to book - Correspondence, notes, and interview questions, 1992-1997 (Box 21, Folder 223)
    - Notes and questions regarding David Baltimore case, undated (Box 21, Folder 224)
    - David Baltimore case research - Correspondence and contacts, 1992-1996 (Box 21, Folder 225)
    - Boston, Massachusetts March 1996 research trip, 1993-1996 (Box 21, Folder 226)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology October 1996 scientific fraud and misconduct seminar (Box 21, Folder 227)
    - Ideas for article on David Baltimore case, 1992-1995 (Box 21, Folder 228)
    - New York and Washington D.C. trips, 1996 (Box 21, Folder 229)
    - Manuscript draft - Alison Wilson copy, 1996-1997 (Box 21, Folder 230)
    - John Heilbron comments on manuscript, 1997 (Box 21, Folder 231)
    - Office of Research Integrity (ORI) Post-Hearing Brief regarding Thereza Imanishi-Kari case, 1995 (Box 21, Folder 232)
    - Department Appeals Board (DAB) Decision regarding Thereza Imanishi-Kari appeal, 1996 (Box 21, Folder 233)
    - Department Appeals Board (DAB) Post-Hearing Brief of Respondent, 1996 (Box 22, Folder 234)
    - Department Appeals Board (DAB) Office of Research Integrity (ORI) Reply to Post-Hearing Brief of Respondent, 1996 (Box 22, Folder 235)
    - Department Appeals Board (DAB) Office of Research Integrity (ORI) Proposed Findings of Fact and Conclusions of Law, 1995 (Box 22, Folder 236-237)
    - Serge Lang 1989-1990 materials regarding David Baltimore case (Box 22, Folder 238)
    - Serge Lang 1991 materials regarding David Baltimore case (Box 22, Folder 239)
    - Serge Lang 1992 materials regarding David Baltimore case (Box 22, Folder 240)
    - Thereza Imanishi-Kari exoneration - News clipping, 1996 August 21 (Box 22, Folder 241)
    - Roy Vagelos, 1997 (Box 22, Folder 242)
    - James D. Watson, 1968-1990 (Box 22, Folder 243)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - David Weaver, 1992-1993 (Box 22, Folder 244)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Robert Woodland, 1992-1993 (Box 22, Folder 245)
    - Daniel Kevles interviews - Henry Wortis, 1984-1996 (Box 23, Folder 246)
    - WGBH - Life: The First Four Billion Years, 1995-1996 (Box 23, Folder 247)
    - Scientific fraud and misconduct - Office of Research Integrity (ORI), 1993-1996 (Box 23, Folder 248)
    - Office of Scientific Integrity (OSI)/Office of Research Integrity (ORI) scientific misconduct procedures, 1986-1997 (Box 23, Folder 249)
    - United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) Public Health Service scientific fraud and misconduct policies and procedures, 1988-1997 (Box 23, Folder 250)
    - Thereza Imanishi-Kari case - Final oral arguments before United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS), 1996 (Box 23, Folder 251)
    - Media response to Thereza Imanishi-Kari appeal ruling, 1996-1997 (Box 23, Folder 252)
    - Office of Research Integrity (ORI) Newsletter issues, 1993-1997 (Box 23, Folder 253)
    - Scientific misconduct - Policies and procedures, 1992-1997 (Box 23, Folder 254)
    - Commission on Research Integrity - Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology (FASEB) letters in response to Commission report, 1996-1997 (Box 23, Folder 255)
    - Commission on Research Integrity report, 1995 (Box 24, Folder 256)
    - David Baltimore case press coverage - Articles, 1991 (Box 24, Folder 257)
    - Office of Research Integrity (ORI) Investigation Report - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, undated (Box 24, Folder 258)
    - Department Appeals Board (DAB) Post-Hearing Brief of Office of Research Integrity (ORI), 1995 (Box 24, Folder 259)
    - Department Appeals Board (DAB) Post-Hearing Brief of Respondent, 1996 (Box 24, Folder 260)
  - Hearings transcripts, 1988-1995; 3; 3.04 Cubic Feet 8 document boxes: 8 letter boxes
    This subseries includes copies of transcripts from various hearings related to the allegations of scientific misconduct against Thereza Imanishi-Kari.
    Most of the files in the subseries pertain to Imanishi-Kari's 1995 appeal of the Office of Research Integrity's (ORI) findings that she conducted scientific misconduct. The hearings were done before the Department Appeals Board (DAB) of the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) between June 1995 and September 1995. DAB decided that ORI had not proven its case against Imanishi-Kari.
    Scope and content notes have been added to the individual HHS proceedings transcript files to describe which witnesses were interviewed in those hearing sessions.
    Within the subseries, there are also transcripts from several hearings of the United States House of Representatives Committee on Energy and Commerce Subcommittee on Oversight and Investigations between 1988 and 1990. The Subcommittee also investigated the allegations of scientific fraud regarding Imanishi-Kari's data in the Cell journal article.
    There are some notes included in the files. The notes give insight into how the transcripts informed Daniel Kevles' writing of his book on the Thereza Imanishi-Kari case.
    - Scientific Fraud - Hearings Before the Subcommittee on Oversight and Investigations, May 4-5, 1989, Serial No. 101-64 (Box 24, Folder 261)
    - Scientific Fraud (Part 2) - Hearings Before the Subcommittee on Oversight and Investigations, April-May 1990, Serial No. 101-187, 1990-1991 (Box 24, Folder 262-263)
    - Fraud in National Institutes of Health (NIH) Grant Programs - Hearing Before the Subcommittee on Oversight and Investigations, April 12, 1988, Serial No. 100-109, 1988-1989 (Box 25, Folder 264-265)
    - Scientific Fraud - Hearings Before the Subcommittee on Oversight and Investigations, May 9, 1989, Serial No. 101-64 (Box 25, Folder 266)
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, June 12-13, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 25, Folder 267-268)
      Witnesses John Dahlberg
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, June 14-15, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 26, Folder 269-270)
      Witnesses John Dahlberg, James Musimann
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, June 16-19, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 26, Folder 271-273)
      Witnesses Austin Barron, Margot O'Toole, James Musimann
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, June 20-21, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 27, Folder 274-275)
      Witnesses Joseph Davie, Walter Gilbert
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, June 22-23, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 27, Folder 276-277)
      Witnesses William McClure, Robert Woodland, Brigitte Huber, Martina Boersch-Supan
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, June 26, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 27, Folder 278-279)
      Witnesses Herman Eisen, David Baltimore
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, June 27-28, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 28, Folder 280-281)
      Witnesses Terence Speed, David Weaver, Martin Dorf, Susan Swain, John Kearney, Norman Klinman
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, June 29, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 28, Folder 282-283)
      Witnesses Moema Reis, Chris Albanese, Terence Speed
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, June 30, 1995, Docket No, A-95-33 (Box 28, Folder 284)
      Witnesses Henry Wortis, J. Donald Capra, Edward Reilly
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, August 21, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 28, Folder 285)
      Witnesses Terence Speed
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, August 22, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 29, Folder 286-287)
      Witnesses Phillipa Merreck, John Hargett
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, August 23, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 29, Folder 288)
      Witnesses John Hargett, Larry Stewart
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, August 24, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 29, Folder 289)
      Witnesses Larry Stewart
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, August 25, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 29, Folder 290-291)
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, August 28, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 30, Folder 292-293)
      Witnesses Gerald Richards, Ward Deharo
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, August 29, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 30, Folder 294-295)
      Witnesses Robert Kuranz, Reynold Verret, Vivien Igras, Thereza Imanishi-Kari
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, August 30, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 30, Folder 296-297)
      Witnesses Thereza Imanishi-Kari, Austin Barron
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, August 31, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 31, Folder 298-299)
      Witnesses Thereza Imanishi-Kari
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, September 1, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 31, Folder 300-301)
      Witnesses Thereza Imanishi-Kari, Larry Stewart
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, September 13, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 31, Folder 302-303)
      Witnesses James Mosimann, Charles Maplethorpe, Lieko Dahlgren
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, September 14, 1995, Docket No. A-95-33 (Box 32, Folder 304-305)
      Witnesses Terence Speed, Margot O'Toole, Vivian Igras, William Fitzgerald, Gerald Richards, Charles Maplethorpe
    - Transcript of Proceedings Before the United States Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) In the matter of Thereza Imanishi-Kari, September 15, 1995, Serial No. A-95-33 (Box 32, Folder 306)
      Witnesses John Dahlbert, Thereza Imanishi-Kari
  - New Yorker article, 1988-1996; 4; .95 Cubic Feet 2.5 document boxes: 2.5 letter boxes
    This subseries contains files that document the background, editing, and aftermath of Daniel Kevles' article "The Assault on David Baltimore". The article was published in the New Yorker in May 1996. Kevles wrote the article about the Thereza Imanishi-Kari scientific misconduct allegation investigations and proceedings while he was researching and preparing his book on the case.
    The subseries chiefly consists of drafts, revisions, and galley proofs of the article sent between Kevles and the New Yorker editor Sharon DeLano. Other files show fact checking on the article, comments on a draft by an associate, and promotion of the article through a press release.
    There are also materials documenting Kevles' proposal for the article, response to the article, and the influence of the article on Kevles' writing of his book. Responses to the article originated from both the press and individuals involved in the Thereza Imanishi-Kari case. Replies from both Kevles and the New Yorker Letters Editor Josselyn Simpson to these responses are contained in the files.
    Correspondence, notes, drafts, galleys, news clips, and articles are found throughout the subseries.
    - New Yorker article "The Assault on David Baltimore", 1996 (Box 32, Folder 307)
    - New Yorker article revisions, 1996 (Box 32, Folder 308)
    - New Yorker article proofs, 1996 (Box 32, Folder 309)
    - New Yorker article April 1996 draft (Box 32, Folder 310)
    - New Yorker article March 1996 draft, 1995-1996 (Box 33, Folder 311)
    - New Yorker article April 1996 draft (Box 33, Folder 312)
    - New Yorker article May 2, 1996 proofs (Box 33, Folder 313)
    - New Yorker article May 9, 1996 proofs (Box 33, Folder 314)
    - New Yorker article May 14-15, 1996 proofs (Box 33, Folder 315)
    - New Yorker article - Letters to New Yorker and New Yorker responses, 1996 (Box 33, Folder 316)
    - New Yorker article - Press release, 1996 (Box 33, Folder 317)
    - New Yorker article fact checking, 1988-1996 (Box 33, Folder 318)
    - New York Review of Books article proposal, 1992 June 13 (Box 33, Folder 319)
    - New Yorker article draft - David Goodstein comments, 1996 (Box 33, Folder 320)
    - Book reorganization in accordance with New Yorker article and article proofs, 1996 (Box 33, Folder 321)
    - New Yorker article March 16, 1996 draft (Box 33, Folder 322)
    - New Yorker article - Section I drafts, 1995 (Box 34, Folder 323)
    - New Yorker article - Section II drafts, 1996 (Box 34, Folder 324)
    - New Yorker article - Section III draft, 1996 (Box 34, Folder 325)
    - New Yorker article - Section IV draft, 1996 (Box 34, Folder 326)
    - New Yorker article - Section V drafts, 1996 (Box 34, Folder 327)
    - New Yorker article revisions, 1996 (Box 34, Folder 328)
    - Response to New Yorker article and Daniel Kevles Chronicle of Higher Education article, 1996 (Box 34, Folder 329)
    - New Yorker article criticism - New York Observer and Chemical and Engineering News, 1996 (Box 34, Folder 330)